Carl W. Ackerman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Carl W. Ackerman Papers 1833-1970 (bulk 1931-1956)
MSS50039
Ackerman, Carl W. (Carl William), 1890-1970
60,000 items 227 containers plus 1 classified and 1 oversize 86 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist, educator, and public relations consultant. Correspondence, diaries, speeches and writings, family papers, scrapbooks, clippings, and other papers relating chiefly to Ackerman's career as a journalist and dean of Columbia University School of Journalism.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Ackerman family.; Ackerman, Carl W. (Carl William), 1890-1970.; Ackerman, Carl W. (Carl William), 1890-1970. George Eastman. 1930.; Ackerman, John F., d. 1942. John F. Ackerman papers. 1860-1942.; Ackerman, Mabel VanderHoof. Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman papers.; Ackerman, Robert V. (Robert VanderHoof). Robert V. Ackerman papers.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Benton, William, 1900-1973--Correspondence.; Bernstein, Herman, 1876-1935--Correspondence.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947--Correspondence.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Castle, William R. (William Richards), 1878-1963--Correspondence.; Cole, Felix, 1887-1969--Correspondence.; Cooper, Kent, 1880-1965--Correspondence.; Dennis, William Cullen, b. 1878--Correspondence.; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969--Correspondence.; Eastman, George, 1854-1932--Correspondence.; Eastman, George, 1854-1932.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Elkus, Abram I., 1867-1947--Correspondence.; Fackenthal, Frank Diehl, 1883-1968--Correspondence.; Freeman, Douglas Southall, 1886-1953--Correspondence.; Gerard, James W. (James Watson), 1867-1951--Correspondence.; Graves, William Sidney, 1865-1940--Correspondence.; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938--Correspondence.; Howard, Roy Wilson, 1883-1964--Correspondence.; Kirk, Grayson L. (Grayson Louis), 1903-1997.; Krock, Arthur, 1886- --Correspondence.; Lawrence, David, 1888-1973--Correspondence.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945--Correspondence.; Pegler, J. Westbrook (James Westbrook), 1894-1969--Correspondence.; Pulitzer, Joseph, 1885-1955--Correspondence.; Pulitzer, Ralph, 1879-1939--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Thomson, Basil, 1861-1939--Correspondence.; Wilson, Hugh Robert, 1885-1946--Correspondence.; Yalman, Ahmet Emin, 1889- --Correspondence.
Organizations
American Society of Newspaper Editors.; American Valuation Association.; Columbia University.; Columbia University. School of Journalism.; Eastman Kodak Company.; Motion Picture Producers and Distributors of America.; Oberlaender Trust.; Pulitzer Prize Board (Columbia University); United Press Associations.; United States. Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938.; United States. National Industrial Recovery Act of 1933.; Washington Cathedral.
Subjects
Censorship.; Freedom of the press.; Germans--United States.; Government and the press.; History, Modern--20th century.; International organization.; Journalism--Awards.; Journalism--Study and teaching--China--Chongqing.; Journalism--Study and teaching--New York (State)--New York.; Journalism--Study and teaching.; Journalism.; Labor--United States.; Lend-lease operations (1941-1945); Public relations--United States.; Universities and colleges--New York (State)--New York.; World War, 1914-1918--Mexico.; World War, 1914-1918--Switzerland.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
Places
China.; East Asia.; Europe--History--1918-1945.; Germany--Emigration and immigration.; Germany--History--1871-1918.; Ireland--History--War of Independence, 1919-1921.; Japan.; Latin America.; Middle East--History--1914-1923.; Russia.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; United States--Economic conditions--1918-1945.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Foreign relations--1933-1945.
Titles
New York times.; Philadelphia public ledger.; Saturday evening post.
Occupations
Educators.; Journalists.; Public relations consultants.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Carl W. Ackerman, journalist, educator, and public relations consultant, were given to the Library of Congress by Ackerman and his estate, 1959-1971.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Photographs, drawings, and prints have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Maps and atlases have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. Recordings and a volume of musical instruction have been transferred to the Music Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Carl W. Ackerman Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Carl W. Ackerman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1890, Jan. 16 Born, Richmond, Ind.
1911 A.B., Earlham College, Richmond, Ind.
1913 B.Litt., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1913-1914 Correspondent, United Press Associations, Albany, N.Y., and Washington, D.C.
1914 Married Mabel L. VanderHoof
1915-1917 Correspondent, United Press Associations, Berlin, Germany
1917 Special writer for New York Tribune Published Germany, the Next Republic? New York: G. H. Doran Co.
1917-1918 Contributor to Saturday Evening Post; trips to Mexico, Spain, France, Switzerland
1918 Published Mexico's Dilemma. New York: G. H. Doran Co.
1918-1919 Correspondent for New York Times in Siberia, China, and Japan
1919 Published Trailing the Bolsheviki. New York: C. Scribner's Sons Toured U.S. for Philadelphia Public Ledger, writing articles on industrial unrest
1920-1921 Organized and served as chief of Philadelphia Public Ledger Foreign News Service, London, England
1922-1928 Corporate public relations work as president of Carl W. Ackerman, Inc., Editorial Research Association, and ERA Publications
1924 Published Dawes-the Doer! New York: Era Publications
1927-1930 Public relations work for the Eastman Kodak Co.
1930 Published George Eastman. New York: Houghton Mifflin Co.
1930-1931 Assistant to the president, General Motors Corp.
1931-1956 Dean, School of Journalism (1931-1935) and Graduate School of Journalism (1935-1956), Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1932-1954 Secretary, Pulitzer Prize Advisory Board, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1935-1936 World trip
1937 Trip to Venezuela
1938 Organized Maria Moors Cabot Prizes for Latin American journalists
1943-1945 Founder and administrator with others of Post-Graduate School of Journalism, Chungking, China
1945 Toured Europe and Asia as member of the American Society of Newspaper Editors World Free Press Mission
1947 Trip to Venezuela
1956 Retired from Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1970, Oct. 9 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Carl William Ackerman (1890-1970) span the years 1833-1970, with the bulk of the material concentrated in 1931-1956 when he was dean of the School of Journalism and Graduate School of Journalism at Columbia University. The collection constitutes an important source for the history of twentieth-century journalism as well as for some of the public questions in which he took an interest, most notably freedom of the press and journalism education. The papers also include documentation of Ackerman's activities as a news correspondent during and after World War I, the scene of which ranged from Germany in 1915-1917, to Siberia in 1918, to American labor unrest in 1919, to the Irish rebellion in 1920-1921. In addition, there are papers concerning his activities as a public relations consultant from 1921 to 1927. The collection consists of Diaries; Family Papers; General Correspondence; Subject File, Speech, Article and Book File; Miscellany; Oversize; and Classified series.
Ackerman enjoyed the acquaintance of many prominent newspaperman, editors, authors, educators, and statesmen. Significant correspondents include Nicholas Murray Butler, William R. Castle, Kent Cooper, William Cullen Dennis, George Eastman, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Frank Diehl Fackenthal, Douglas Southall Freeman, James W. Gerard, Edward Mandel House, Roy Wilson Howard, Arthur Krock, David Lawrence, Joseph Pulitzer (1885-1955), Ralph Pulitzer, and Franklin D. Roosevelt.
The collection includes items from the years 1915-1917, when Ackerman served as United Press correspondent within the Central Powers. There are notes, research materials, and scrapbooks relating to the hundreds of dispatches he filed from Berlin, many of which appeared as front-page stories in the American press. Diaries for this period are scant, but letters to various family members by both Ackerman and his wife, Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman, provide a narrative of the life of an American correspondent in wartime Europe.
After the break in United States diplomatic relations with Germany in 1917, Ackerman served as a special correspondent for the Saturday Evening Post and gathered material in Switzerland, Mexico, and elsewhere concerning political events in the years 1917-1918. While working for the Post, Ackerman served simultaneously as a confidential reporter to Edward Mandell House, President Wilson's adviser, and began an exchange of letters that ended only with House's death in 1938. At the end of World War I, Ackerman and House corresponded on such subjects as the League of Nations, press censorship, Russia, and Japan. On July 16, 1919, House wrote Ackerman: "I shall always regret that you were not in Paris during the Peace Conference. You would have been helpful in many directions and I constantly missed your not being here." Subject files for Switzerland and Siberia contain copies of reports written by Ackerman for House and the United States Department of State.
One of the most dramatic episodes in Ackerman's career was a trip to Siberia for the New York Times in the fall of 1918 to investigate the reported execution of Czar Nicholas II of Russia and his family. Ackerman's papers document his slow journey of five thousand miles across the Trans-Siberian Railway to the village of Ekaterinburg, where he interviewed eyewitnesses to the event and lived in a hired railway boxcar. Subject files for Siberia and the New York Times include some of Ackerman's notes and dispatches. Correspondence concerning Siberia is in files for Newton Diehl Baker, Herman Bernstein, Felix Cole, Allen W. Dulles, Abram I. Elkus, William Sidney Graves, and Hugh Wilson. Reminiscences are to be found in some later speeches, articles, and letters. There are also subject files for China and Japan dating from this period.
A large group in the Subject File series concerns the Philadelphia Public Ledger Foreign News Service, which Ackerman organized and headed from 1920 to 1921. These files concern the activities of the dozen or so correspondents under his direction in Europe and the Near East, as well as his own writing. There is much about the European scene, including a group of Ackerman's own dispatches filed from the League of Nations Assembly in Geneva in 1920, but the most interesting episode is Ackerman's coverage of the Sinn Fein rebellion in Ireland. The British Government allowed Ackerman to make a number of trips from his base in London to Dublin to seek out Michael Collins, the militant leader of the Irish Republican Army, for a rare series of interviews. Ackerman was guaranteed safe passage in return for sounding out the Irish leaders on possible peace terms. There is correspondence with Sir Basil Thomson, chief of the intelligence services of Scotland Yard, and with Collins himself. Much of Ackerman's diary for 1920-2921, his "London Notes," deals with the Irish question; it also includes his observations about Colonel House, who was then a member of Ackerman's Public Ledger staff.
In 1921, Ackerman left newspaper reporting to become a public relations consultant, and there are subject files for firms and organizations with which he was associated, including the American Valuation Association, the Eastman Kodak Company, the Motion Picture Producers and Distributors of America, Inc., and the Washington Cathedral.
In 1930, the largest of Ackerman's five published books appeared, the biography George Eastman, based on extensive interviews with Eastman's papers. As in the case of many of Ackerman's writings, there are accompanying files of source material and correspondence.
By far the largest group of subject files concerns Ackerman's twenty-five year tenure as dean of the Columbia University School of Journalism. The files contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed material relating to internal changes and controversies at Columbia under the presidencies of Nicholas Murray Butler, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and Grayson L. Kirk, as well as documentation of Ackerman's own innovations in the School of Journalism.
During his Columbia years Ackerman corresponded with a great number of public figures. fellow journalists, and Columbia alumni, many of whom were scattered throughout the world. Much of this correspondence deals with the effect of national and international events upon journalism and the relation of governments to the press, especially in matters of censorship and propaganda. There is material in the Columbia University subject files and in files for the American Newspaper Publishers Association and American Society of Newspaper Editors concerning the possible effect on press freedom of certain provisions of the National Industry Recovery Act of 1933, the Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938, and the Lend-Lease Bill of 1941.
Some fairly typical exchanges of correspondence are as follows: in 1939-1940, Ackerman corresponded with William R. Castle about President Roosevelt's foreign policy and potential American involvement in the European war; in 1945, with General George S. Patton (1885-1945) about freedom of expression; in 1946, with William Benton, assistant secretary of state, concerning the government's international information program; in 1948, with Westbrook Pegler on the subject of journalism education; and in 1959, with the Turkish journalist Ahmed Emin Yalman shortly after the latter had been sentenced to prison for articles criticizing the Turkish Government.
The Speech, Article, and Book File includes speeches and articles by Ackerman during his years at Columbia, accompanied by correspondence that provides a sampling of public reaction. There is such a file in the case of his speech of October 21, 1942, "Freezing the Press," delivered in the wake of a Justice Department suit against the Associated Press and 1,275 daily newspapers, in which Ackerman asserted his belief that wartime government restrictions on news were dangerous. A correspondence file also accompanies a 1953 article on civil liberties entitled "Is Political Conformity Forced upon Students?"
One interesting subject file is that for the Pulitzer Prize Advisory Board, of which Ackerman served as secretary. There are memoranda, correspondence, and minutes documenting the selection of some award winners and controversies within the board. Also included are transcripts of correspondence as early as 1921, antedating Ackerman's tenure on the board.
Ackerman was instrumental in organizing and administering the Maria Moors Cabot Prizes in inter-American journalism, and the subject file for the Cabot Prizes includes much information concerning Latin American journalism. Additional materials on Latin America, including correspondence and scrapbooks, are in subject files dealing with Ackerman's frequent trips to the Southern Hemisphere. Similar subject files deal with his trips to the Far East, as well as with his role in establishing the Post-Graduate School of Journalism in Chungking, China, in 1943-1945.
A subject file for the Oberlaender Trust of Philadelphia, of which Ackerman was a trustee, contains information on the trust's work in financing the relocation of displaced German scholars and students in the United States after the rise of Adolph Hitler. In 1932 the trust was the first philanthropic organization in the United States to grant a stipend to Albert Einstein.
Another subject file concerns Ackerman's part in a 1945 three-man mission of the American Society of Newspaper Editors that made, with the approval of the government, a forty thousand mile world tour to promote freedom of the press in the postwar settlement. Of particular interest are Ackerman's lengthy letters to his wife, written almost daily, that record his observations on the political and social situation in over a dozen countries in the last months of World War II. The originals of these letters are in the Family Papers series; they are also compiled as the typescript of an unpublished book, The Right Road to Peace in the Speech, Article, and Book File.
Ackerman's last major writing was an anecdotal and critical history of Columbia University, chiefly concerned with the presidencies of Nicholas Murray Butler and Dwight D. Eisenhower. Entitled “Eisenhower in Wonderland,” it was completed in 1958, following Ackerman's retirement from Columbia, but not published.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
Diaries, 1909-1969
Family Papers, 1860-1970
General Correspondence, 1907-1970
Subject File, 1908-1970
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1909-1964
Miscellany, 1833-1970
Oversize
Classified
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm73050039
Container List
- Diaries, 1909-1969 (Box 1-9)
  Diaries, diary notes, and address books kept by Ackerman and his wife, Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Diaries (Box 1)
    - 1909
    - 1911, 1915
    - 1920-1921, "London Notes" Includes attached correspondence of: Michael Collins, G. F. N. Macready, and Basil H. Thomson
    - 1924-1925
    - 1931-1933
    - 1932-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1945 (Box 3)
    - 1946-1948 (Box 4)
    - 1949-1953 (Box 5)
    - 1954-1957 (Box 6)
    - 1958-1969 (Box 7)
  - Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman (wife) (Box 8)
    - Diary notes, 1915
    - Diaries
      - 1932-1939
      - 1942-1943
      - 1945-1948
      - 1949 (Box 9)
      - 1951-1954
  - Address books
- Family Papers, 1860-1970 (Box 10-25)
  Letters sent and received between family members.
  Arranged chronologically within each file. Includes Ackerman's correspondence with his wife, Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman, and their correspondence with their respective families. Also included are the personal papers of Ackerman's father, John F. Ackerman, and his son, Robert V. Ackerman. Letters of condolence on the death of several family members are arranged alphabetically by correspondent within each file.
  - Correspondence with Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman, 1917-1954, undated (Box 10)
  - Mabel VanderHoof Ackerman (Box 11)
    - Correspondence with Edith M. Smith, 1910-1945
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1917-1954, undated
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1952-1954, 1959 (Box 13)
    - Condolences on death of, 1954
      - A-P
      - Q-Z and miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Correspondence with Ackerman family
    - Charlotte Ackerman
    - Douglas VanderHoof Ackerman
    - Douschka Sweets Ackerman
    - Everett Ackerman
    - Henry Sweets Ackerman
    - John F. and Mary Ackerman
      - 1910-1915
      - 1916-1942, undated (Box 15)
    - Mary Lester Ackerman
    - Michael Lester Ackerman
    - Rhea Ackerman
    - Sallie Blair Ackerman
  - John F. Ackerman (Box 16)
    - Papers, 1860-1942
      - Business papers
      - Miscellaneous personal papers
      - Richmond, Ind., miscellany
    - Condolences on death of, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence with VanderHoof family
    - Douglas VanderHoof, 1917-1957, undated
    - Emma F. VanderHoof
      - 1902-Sept. 1915
      - Oct. 1915-Dec. 1921 (Box 18)
      - 1922-1936, undated (Box 19)
    - Nancy S. VanderHoof
  - Emma F. VanderHoof miscellany
  - Correspondence with son, Robert VanderHoof Ackerman
    - 1918-1942
    - 1943-1958, undated (Box 20)
  - Robert V. Ackerman
    - Correspondence concerning education of
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
    - Miscellaneous personal papers (Box 21)
    - Student papers
    - Student papers (Box 22)
    - Student papers (Box 23)
    - Student papers (Box 24)
    - Condolences on death (Box 25)
    - Estate
  - Sweets, Henry H., correspondence, 1939-1949
  - Family history miscellany
- General Correspondence, 1907-1970 (Box 26-33)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, memoranda, and miscellaneous attachments..
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically
  - "A" miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Abbot, Willis J.
  - Addington, Sarah
  - Anderson, Dwight
  - Angel, John
  - Armour, Norman
  - Auchincloss, Gordon
  - "B" miscellaneous
  - Baillie, Hugh
  - Baker, Newton Diehl
  - Barbey, Daniel E.
  - Barton, Bruce
  - Batchelor, Bronson
  - Batchelor, C.D.
  - Bemis, Samuel Flagg
  - Bernays, Edward L.
  - Bernstein, Herman
  - Bickel, Karl A.
  - Bidwell, Mary
  - Bingay, Malcolm W.
  - Borah, William Edgar
  - Borglum, Gutzon
  - Boyd, Julian P.
  - Braden, Spruille
  - Bretherton, Cyril H.
  - Brown, James Wright
  - Brown, Sevellon
  - Bryce, James
  - Bullitt, William C.
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray
  - "C" miscellaneous
  - Cabot, Godfrey Lowell
  - Calhoun, Crede H.
  - Carter, J. F. C.
  - Castle, William R.
  - Chadbourne, William M. (Box 27)
  - Cole, Felix L.
  - Cooper, Kent
  - Cowles, John
  - Curley, Edward W.
  - Curran, Thomas R.
  - "D" miscellaneous
  - Daniels, Freeman J.
  - Daniels, Josephus
  - Davis, Edgar B.
  - Dawson, William
  - deCourcy, Kenneth
  - DeGaulle, Charles
  - Dennis, William Cullen
  - DeVault, V. T.
  - Devol, Edmund
  - Dewey, Thomas E.
  - Dieli, Anne
  - Donegan, Horace H. B.
  - Dowling, Noel
  - Dreyfus, Louis G.
  - Dulles, Allen W.
  - "E" miscellaneous
  - Early, Joseph J.
  - Early, Stephen T.
  - Edwards, C. Bland
  - Eichelberger, Robert L.
  - Elkus, Abram I.
  - "F" miscellaneous
  - Farley, James A.
  - Feeger, Luther M.
  - Fellers, Bonner F.
  - Finger, John W. (Box 28)
  - Finley, John H.
  - Fleisher, B. W.
  - Forrest, Wilbur
  - Foulke, William Dudley
  - Frankfurter, Felix
  - Fraser, Leon
  - Freeman, Douglas Southall
  - Fritchey, Clayton
  - Furnas, Paul J.
  - "G" miscellaneous
  - Gannett, Frank
  - Garside, Charles
  - Gellhorn, Alfred
  - Gelpi, Sergio G.
  - Gerard, James W.
  - Gibson, Hugh
  - Glenn, C. Leslie
  - Glynn, Martin H.
  - Goodrich, James P.
  - Gordon J. Bennett
  - Grant-Smith, U.
  - Graves, William S.
  - Grew, Joseph C.
  - Grimm, Peter
  - "H" miscellaneous
  - Hadley, Clyde M.
  - Hamilton, J. R.
  - Hanson, Elisha
  - Harriman, W. Averell
  - Harris, George W.
  - Harris, Julian LaRose
  - Hassett, William D.
  - Hawkins, William W.
  - Hillman, William (Box 29)
  - Hoelscher, Gustave H.
  - Hogate, Kenneth C.
  - Hohenberg, John
  - Hoover, Herbert
  - Horinouchi, Kensuke
  - House, Edward Mandell
  - Howard, Roy Wilson
  - Howe, Louis McHenry
  - Howell, Clark
  - Huergo, Maria Constanza
  - Hull, Cordell
  - Hunt, Edgar W.
  - Hymans, Paul
  - Izakov, Boris R.
  - "J" miscellaneous
  - Johnson, Howard
  - "K" miscellaneous
  - Kander, Allen
  - Keller, James
  - Kelly, Robert L.